this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this is Robert bloomin editor
of software engineering radio if you're
hearing this that means you're a
listener of the show but have you ever
thought about being a host it's a great
way to talk to some of the most
interesting people in the industry and
get 30 to 40 thousand people to hear
your thoughts
contact us team @ SC - radio net for
more information are you looking for a
better way to track your engineering
backlog do you want a project management
tool that's both powerful and a joy to
use give clubhouse a try designed for
software teams clubhouse is a fast
modern alternative to conventional
project management tools that are either
too complex or too simple start your
free trial and get 2 extra free months
at clubhouse dot IO / SC radio hello
this is Adam Gordon bell for software
engineering radio today I'm speaking
with Gabriel Gonzalez creator of the
doll configuration language and author
of popular blog haskell for all Gabe
welcome to software engineering radio
also thank you for having me on this
it's an honor to be here it's great to
hear so today we'll be talking about
configuration and configuration
programming languages and and one called
doll day that you have created I think
eventually we'll get into complicated
configuration problems but I'd like to
start off with some some simple
definitions so what is configuration in
the world of software development so I
like to think of it in terms of what's
the problem that configuration files or
configuration formats solve
configuration files often arise when we
want the end-user to make changes to our
software
without being to install any sort of
programming language toolchain or having
to rebuild a new executable and so forth
because those sorts of requirements are
non-starters for most of our end-users
who might be non-technical for example
sometimes you can kind of avoid those
issues so for example if your
programming language is interpreted then
like for example like JavaScript where
the interpreter is their browser then it
might be fine to write just configure
the program in the same language in fact
you see lots of like you know live you
know test HTML CSS JavaScript
combinations in your browser and that
works because these are already has the
interpreter installed so there's no
other expectation from them on the other
hand if you're poor if your host
programming language is say Haskell
which has which is a compiled language
usually has a very large sprawling tool
chain you might not want to ask users to
install that if they want to configure
your program so that's the kind that's
the high level requirement for that
configurations like dissolved make it
easy for users to customize program
behavior with little to no effort on
their part ideally it should be in a
format that's easy for them to
understand easy to modify doesn't
require too much technical understanding
or expertise so that's how I think of
configuration languages so in your job
like what type of things like what's an
example of something you would put in
configuration so users could modify that
an example of a I don't know if this
really qualifies as a configuration but
at our job we distribute sets of content
for for network threat hunting or a
cyber security startup users can create
sort of like little mini programs kind
of like Wireshark like a little bit more
powerful they can publish and subscribe
to them and those packages of program
definitions are kind of in this case
they're Dahl files but you could think
of them maybe like JSON files right
they're just sort of like lists of
records each record contains like maybe
some definition some metadata stuff like
that just some configuration that's an
example what we do we might use it up
for at work another example might be
like deployment configuration right like
saying like you know I want all these
machines to have this particular setting
there's you know X machines here their
IP addresses hostname
so forth that's another example of a
common configuration scenario that
arises at our work what's the most
complicated configuration file that
you've come across probably I think
kubernetes is usually the one that most
people think of what I think of
complicated configuration at least like
an open source yeah when I worked at
Twitter Twitter had some very large
configurations for example Twitter had
its own internal bit taking the open
source tool but it's mostly used by
Twitter called pants which is kind of
like a Python version of basil like
Google's build tool and the the build
configurations there for like brawl
Twitter's mono repo were quite large as
well and what what type of problems or
are there problems with a very large and
complex configuration that you might see
with a kubernetes can take very large
and repetitive so I'm sure many people
in the audience might be familiar with
the design principle don't repeat
yourself besides the fact that software
engineers or programmers in ghent in
general are lazy right we want the
computer to do more of the work for us
so we don't want our Peter cells but
it's not just out of laziness and
authoring the configuration file but
it's also laziness and maintaining it
because if you make if you keep copying
and pasting configuration sections over
and over I saw this a lot of Twitter for
example for pants right there a lot of
people who just didn't really understand
the configuration lanes for bills like
you know pants wasn't used very much
outside of Twitter so when they join
they were really sure how to use it so
they just take they're just copy and
paste configuration sections from things
they do to work and then slightly tweak
them and upon when you do that well
there's several problems one is that
it's like it's hard to maintain because
now anytime you need to make a change
you need to find all the copy and pasted
versions and make the matching change
second you're not even really sure if
it's the right thing to do to modify all
the matching versions because when you
copy and paste something you lose the
original intent right because you're
basically create exact replica of the
original configuration section are you
really saying I want all these
configuration feels to be exactly these
ones or are you really saying I want it
to be the same as that thing over there
with this one tweak that in like in the
in the course of copying and pasting it
you lose that information that intention
that
make sense that's my experience working
with well builds in general like
whenever I need to get a new Jenkins
build going I feel like I find a similar
service and and start with whatever it
had yeah yeah I understand
so besides dull which we'll get into
like what formats are most popular for
configuration it depends on the domain
so for example for build tools like
Python or basil
it tends to be a custom format like I
think skylark or pants had like this
Python ish language Nix is another bat
it's another analogous thing to basil it
has its own custom language for ops yeah
well and JSON very common in that domain
for like UNIX software development maybe
any files or maybe some ad hoc format
like the alsa audio configuration format
though yeah so it really depends a lot
on the domain but I know and I 10 at
work I do a lot of ups in infrastructure
related stuff so I tend to interact more
with JSON and yamo as a configuration
format you mentioned this problem that
the yeah Mille can have I assume or or
JSON or ini files this is the
duplication of you know repetitive code
a repetitive configuration so one
solution I've seen for this in the past
is like you know like a C++ application
will use like Lua as its configuration
language or like chef uses Ruby right so
you're like hey I have the full power of
a programming language at my fingertips
right so is that a good idea are the
downsides to that so one of the upsides
of that is that you you can deliver a
lot of customization potential to users
and I think one of the more commonly
cited downsides even if the language is
easy to distribute easy to interpret is
that it can lead to configuration files
which are very difficult for people to
understand because there's a tension in
software engineering in general and also
for programming languages or
configuration formats specifically which
is that generally the easier you make it
to write something the harder you make
it for other people to read and
vice-versa the easier the more you you
force it to be easy to read the more you
have to constrain it and make it harder
to write
so generally the more powerful the
configuration format the more difficult
it can be for other people to understand
or comprehend what's going on and that's
what you don't want in a configuration
format you want to be easy to understand
easy to analyze
he's very often configuration file
mistakes are one of the most common
sources of outages and production
failures there's a post written by I
believe Dan Lew where he talked about
post mortems at Google and that I
believe he said that one of the most
common sources of runtime failures was
just due to invalid configuration files
and often people don't test or review
configuration files well to the same
standard that they view code and that's
one of the reasons why it can be
difficult to safely change them and so
that's why you want Kabira files to be
very easy to comprehend so that it makes
it easier to understand and potentially
prevent these sorts of runtime failures
you mentioned I think before that you
work on some sort of network security
product I assumed that there could also
be concerns that if I'm allowing a full
interpreter to run in my configuration
layer that could be a security risk do
you view that as such sure yes there in
fact one thing I haven't talked about is
so far I've been kind of implicitly
assuming that we're configuring let's
say an executable that the user has
install our system but there's other
ways we can deliver code to users so for
example like we could host a service
that either the users interact with
directly through an API or a front-end
web app that interacts with that service
indirectly for us or maybe we're
delivering JavaScript code which the
user is running in their own browser and
we don't want to and it's especially in
the case where we're running a service
hosted in our own datacenter accepting
API calls from potentially untrusted
users we don't want to be running
arbitrary code which the users are
handing to us that's a huge security
vulnerability so for example that could
be used to maybe just delete stuff on
our production servers or leak secrets
or do all sorts of harmful things so we
really want to restrict what
configuration formats can do in order to
keep the whatever environment they're
executing in as safe as possible so are
you speaking of a scenario in which you
have a cloud hosted service but various
customers can
like bringing their own configuration to
the service yeah exactly
I ideally I want to make that possible
that's what that's one of my goals no
that's interesting I haven't come across
that before so it sounds like to me
there is there's configuration that's
like declarative on one side that you're
talking about that's like yeah MO and
then on the other side there is like
using something much more flexible and
you're saying the downside there's a
trade-off right one's easier to read
one's easier to write to write okay yeah
so what does Dahl bring to this
distinction I guess what is dolls reason
for existing so dolls cynic women is
that doll is not turing-complete
so it's funny because the way doll
originated was just to answer a very
common question I had when reading posts
like let's say on the programming
subreddit or hacker news or Twitter
where people would be arguing about the
virtues of various configuration
approaches like should we use just an
inert file format like Jason or animals
should we use a full-blown programming
language to customize our configurations
and one of the very common themes that
comes out of those discussions is that
when people talked about when people
would say that you need to use a
programming language to configure it
because if they need the full power
the most common counter to that was I
don't want to use a configuration format
that's turing-complete
I'm not exactly sure whether people
actually cared about Turing completeness
per se or maybe it was just like a
umbrella for other things that they
actually cared about but I decided to
ask the question you know okay what if I
gave you a programming language that was
not turing-complete
to configure your programs which you and
so it give you all the experts if you
want but enough restriction that you
couldn't do dumb things in this language
would you still be okay with that in
terms of like some people thought yeah
that is exactly the balance that I was
trying to strike what what does it mean
for a language to be not turned complete
I mean so there's a pedantic definition
but I'll just say I think it's close
enough to say that you can't if it's not
Turing complete then all programs can
halt or at least you can you can
statically know if they're gonna haul in
practice for dala it just means that all
programs are going to halt
it doesn't guarantee things like when
it's got a hole right could take longer
than the heat death of the universe I'll
be dead by then before hulls right but
at least at some point if we wait long
enough is gonna terminate right he's not
gonna go into an endless loop or hang or
anything like that I'm trying to fit
this in the context of what you said
earlier so there's a full programming
language and then there's a declarative
format and then you're saying the
advantage of Dahl is that it can
complete running whatever the step is
that turns it into a declarative format
is is limited yes like if I had a ruby
file that was my configuration if I was
actually able to just run it and then at
the end it produced yamo then that would
be in an inert format by evaluating it
I've made it inert well he's not just
like if I fall used to do is just run
like a doll that's something that Ruby
does not do right because if your result
is just a record then you can
technically run any programming language
to produce that record that makes sense
I'd like to maybe approach what it all
looks like by by comparing it maybe to
something simpler so if I were to write
like a JSON format right then like I
have access to a certain amount of
primitive types right and I kind of
build up like a an object structure like
a I guess it's basically like a tree but
you can nest things inside of each other
so what primitives does Dahl have for
for holding data so first off it has the
same primitives JSON has it has records
or I guess what some people might call
dictionaries or Maps it has lists there
are strings has pools it has unlimited
precision integers which is very
important that when you're comparing to
JSON which yes and it basically has like
it also has some things like JSON does
not have so it has a built-in support
for enum so you don't have to use a
string you can like statically declare
it could only be one of these possible
values it actually supports a
generalization of enums which are I
think commonly called some types mm-hmm
can say statically it can only be one of
these possible types of values the
maybe a payload associated with each
alternative type it could be and they're
tagged so you know which one you're
looking at and whenever you're trying to
inspect it to decide what to do with it
you can actually like kind of just
convert a JSON file to a doll file by
like replace replacing colons with
equals and maybe removing quotes around
the the key names or field names and
diction dictionaries and then they both
kind of look the same
oh well but it it doesn't stop there
right because I I think that I saw type
annotations on is that correct is there
typing aspect to the language yes so
doll is a real programming language so a
lot of things that are normally done
separately in free computation form as
configuration formats like JSON are
built into the language so for example
at what a configuration format would
call a schema like JSON schema is just a
type annotation and doll so that that's
the Dahle analog of a schema and same
thing like it was templating right so a
template in doll is just a function
whose input is a record of things you
want to use the template with and whose
output is a string that has been where
you've interpolate Athiya want a
template so because dolls real
programming language like you doesn't
need to add special case support for a
lot of these features which
configuration form a tough to add on
they're just built in by virtue of being
a real language so it starts it has
these basic datatypes it has some
additional types then it has type
annotations and then you've mentioned
functions so this is where we start to
cross into more of a programming
language type concept right yes
now we're evaluating things we're
passing in arguments so you can define
functional the primitive there is an
anonymous function so like what Python
programs might call lambda and you can
optionally assign ningke's to anything
including anonymous functions so they're
no longer anonymous you can give them
names and you can apply them to
arguments just like in a programming
language and they're highly restricted
right so because it's not
turing-complete
a function cannot call itself recursions
banned from the language and also
supports variables so you can use a
to say like let x equals 1 and now you
can refer to x over and over again in
studying how to repeat yourself
presumably it's more useful if X is
something bigger than one but you get
the idea is the is the purpose behind
the functions to do with this original
idea you mentioned like taking the
repetitiveness out of a configuration
format is that is that Y bringing
functions to this format is valuable yes
the primary reason is again going back
to we don't want to repeat ourselves
both to make it easier to write easier
to maintain and easier to preserve the
original intent we have a single source
of truth for everything in the format
then whenever we need to make a change
we only need to change one place in the
codebase and it may not sound like a big
deal when you're small company but when
you work in a large company like Twitter
in a mono repo which has a huge number
of files then being able to centralize
all logic in one place is a very big
deal in fact I remember back when I was
at Twitter someone just went through
Twitter and then studied like what was
the largest was like what were the most
commonly used programming languages at
the company by lines of code so the
third place was Java second place was
Scala in first place technically not a
language was yam Allah code was far and
away the largest source of code quotes
in the codebase and that was again
because you just Yambol doesn't have
facilities to remove repetitions so they
just had to add a whole bunch of weight
and that weight reduces your agility as
a company if I did every time we had
these large changes and refactor x' we
had to do at the company we would take
like our crack programmers our principal
engineers who would use like these you
know powerful text transformation tools
that they would run over the entire code
base which i think was like maybe 40
gigabytes in size at the time not just
code not many binaries anything like
that and then they put up these gigantic
floor requests where everybody would get
pinged on them because like they'd be
touching every single project and
everybody wasn't coming over for coding
or for something that had been touched
by that full request and then there the
floor cross subscription it would say
something like you know I haven't really
checked this I just did this automatic
transfer
and I guess it builds and I'm not gonna
wait for everybody to approve all these
changes I'm just going to like merge
after a few days if nobody objects and
that was kind of like what people have
to do when you don't have any facilities
for managing a large amounts repetition
yeah that sounds horrible programming by
search and replace basically yes so I'm
thinking back to your original scenario
maybe this story you just talked about
so like you have all these everybody's
copying pasting somebody else's build
file with a bunch of yanil in it so now
that we have functions
I'm guessing weekend like what do we do
do we extract it out to some common
location where and then all I have to do
is is basically call some build function
and pass in like the couple of
differences that my project has is that
the use case yes so here's an
interesting example right let's say
you're trying to distribute a package
right an open-source package right
usually there's a lot of boilerplate for
for open source packages that's shared
between them like let's say a lot of
Haskell projects especially for
companies are just you know possible
framework of like wrapping some some
choice of server maybe the pick ups pick
a blest server library and be a blessed
JSON handling library and one of the
other blessed libraries right and they
just would say we all want these
projects to follow the same format and
with just a few tweaks maybe just change
the package name change the list of
modules in this project but otherwise we
want them all to use a standard format
in practice you just have to like keep
copying pasting the COBOL file to follow
that exact format and again you run to
the same issues as before you'd be nice
if you could just have a central say
like this is the blessed set of packages
for novice Haskell programmers to write
a web server that does something useful
and it's just a function right give me
the name of your package give me a few
other parameters and I'll just do the
rest for you and you can get going right
that's the dream right there and not
just providing and not just providing a
function but providing it easy to obtain
format because one feature that Dell
provides is the ability to import
configuration file formats mm-hmm if you
ever use DM oh I know lots of companies
I think Twitter included if I remember
correctly like they hacked together of
some non-standard thing feature into ml
to import files or include support which
is missing from the ml standard
in order to distribute the configuration
over multiple files yeah the imports
kind of closes that makes it so now I
can pull in from some location so can I
what kind of locations can I pull in
from is it like my local path is it the
web is it github or so Dahl lets you
import from local file paths so like
relative paths absolute paths you can
import from environment variables
arbitrary expressions you can also
import from the web so you can given a
URL which hosts a utf-8 Dahl's encoded
dual source code you can just fetch it
an expression from that and it will
embed it into the program as if you had
just written it there what's neat about
dollas is not just the fact that you can
import from remote expressions safely
but the actual syntax for doing so I
like a lot of programming language is
the way you import something as you say
like at the top of your file you know
import food bar from some package and
bring these names in to scope me and so
forth in dal like given some path to
some other expression it's like a local
path or URL you can just copy and paste
that anywhere in the syntax tree it will
be as if you had copy and pasted I mean
in a principled way as if you had
embedded that expression directly there
into this in the syntax tree ah
interesting so you can say like 1 plus
example.com / foo right example.com /
food contains a number in it it'll fetch
that number and add it to 1 and then
that's it's a very lightweight way of
distributing polishing expressions and
subscribing to them you don't need to
like you know create some package with
some metadata file and upload it to some
package repository and then add it as a
dependency and install it right you just
you know create a URL paste it and
that's the mechanism of distribution
it's it seems very flexible I can
understand how this would be great
removing all this duplication within
Twitter I guess possibly it sounds like
it could bring up more security
ramifications because now I'm pulling an
arbitrary code into my configuration
process yes so dolls support for
importing from URLs is is the most
controversial feature or the language
but the language is actually languages
built from the ground up to take into
account language considered security
concerns
so probably the strongest
thing the language offers is that it's
not only not train complete because
again train complete is just sort of an
umbrella term for things that we
actually care about it's a sandbox
language meaning is pure so you can't
actually like really do anything and all
other than compete a pure value right
the only side effects the language
permits is to fetch things from from
URLs or from file pass or so forth all
right but it can't for example can't
delete a file you can't use to upload
something to it like some secret
sensitive file or secret to s3 you all
sound like you you know I'm sure many
people you guys are thinking like oh I'm
pretty sure I could craft some clever
way to exfiltrate data like through
choice of headers or things are the
choice of the path that I eat that I
choose to import from but dull actually
as already is a step ahead of you has
already thought through that so for
example remote paths or any path really
cannot be computed so you can't leak
program state through the choice of to
the choice of path that you request
paths or resolve all paths are strictly
resolved so you can't use the fet
whether or not a path was requested to
determine what the state of the program
was if paths can be pinned so like if
you import something from actually all
paths even even local ones but
especially remote ones they can be
protected with a hash which is
technically called a semantic integrity
check and if the and that essentially
freezes the import so that if the import
ever changes in any way you will they
will be rejected to prevent somebody
from injecting you behavior into your
program that you did not expect so
there's all sorts of protections in
there that you wouldn't know from first
glance just from hearing the fact that
Dahl allows you to import from URLs
summers longer days and slower pace
invite us to pick up a book follow our
questions and try our hand at something
new the work of modern software
developers is evolving in ways that are
both challenging and rewarding as a
developer it's essential that you
cultivate a security mindset to help we
put together a collection of information
security books podcasts blogs and
hands-on exercises recommended by very
coders across our development security
and product teams from a just published
page-turner to classic frack articles
there's something here for everyone
who's interested in becoming more
security minded so dip your toes in or
take a deep dive visit
www.ohp.parks.ca.gov/governorsawards
when doll gets imported into some
language after it's been evaluated right
it exists as like I'm assuming some sort
of dictionaries of values at the time
the configuration comes into your
language you have some sort of inert
data structures and Dahl has support for
that but also has support for functions
so that you can take out duplication and
then import so that you can kind of hold
these these things somewhere else that
can be shared and then you can use that
to import things that can be from
anywhere it can be from the web and that
sounds scary but you're saying oh but
remember I said it's it's non
turing-complete so there's no way that
it can like loop forever when I try to
import some of some code and then you
also said that it's pure so explained
pure pure means it has very limited set
of side effects so I mean pure really
depends on what matters to the
programmer right so like everything
technically has side effects right you
know I'm taking up CPU or ran out or
network bandwidth or disk or maybe I'm
modifying some registers under the hood
because that's how everything's
implemented so it really depends on what
matters to the programmer so pure in
this context means that we're sort of
ignoring performance characteristics
right maybe maybe some languages would
care about performance characteristics
like rust for example and I'm also
designed alike I don't really care about
fetching things from URL cuz like
especially if I pin it with a hash
it's basically pure right it doesn't
really matter where I get it from as
long as the final result is the same
matches that hash right it's effectively
pure so we don't have like a set of
blessed side-effects and non blessed
side effects so the blest side effects
are evaluation fetching things the non
blest side effects are things like
deleting files uploading things anything
harmful that a malicious code could used
to somehow exploit our system so pure is
an imprecise term which just means that
like it's it's safe to reuse as a
configuration language because the end
results of the evaluation will always
just be this in their data structure so
it won't be writing things to disk or
etc exhibit well even then you can
there's a cache so like when you protect
something with integrity check then
since we know it's never gonna change
we can just cash it in a content
addressable store locally so that we
never need to fetch it again and again
that slightly improves security because
then it means we only need to fetch
something once and then people after
that we never need to make it remote
outbound call ever again
but even then like it's a content
addressable store it's append-only
so it's effectively pure from the users
point of view right it's just the
transparent optimization as far as
they're concerned I think that you
mentioned earlier that it would be
possible to write a doll configuration
that that never completed is that a
concern or something that we should be
concerned about with this tool well what
I never completed you mean like never
completes in our lifetimes but it will
eventually complete okay for me it's
it's not really a concern so for me like
the benefit of being turing-complete is
well there are lots of benefits one is
that in practice it's harder to write
programs that take a long time to run
part of the reason is just because it's
hard to do so by accident like again
we've banned for kerza from the language
so you just got to change how you do
things when you change how to do things
that changes your mental model it's very
similar to how when you switch from a
dynamic language to a typed language it
requires you to adopt a certain mental
discipline you didn't have before and
programming in a in a non Turing
complete language it's the exact same
transition you acquire a new mental
discipline and you start to think about
your code in a different way and both
just the feature itself and it mental
discipline mean you just tend to have
fewer long-running programs and also
like in order to be trained complete you
have to get all sorts of other things
right which are good things in and of
themselves to get right like you got to
have a type system or some sort of a
static analysis to even be able to say
that you're not Turing complete because
if you don't there's lots of ways you
can create infinite loops so what so it
restricts you from doing recursion are
there other restrictions put in place to
meet this moniker non Turing complete
basically it's actually very simple to
write a language that's not Turing
complete for people slightly more
familiar with type theory you take any
hindley-milner type system or for people
even more familiar with type theory
if you take system F and you just ban
recursion it's automatically not turn
complete and somewhat useful language if
you just add some useful primitive
operations so it's it's actually really
easy to make something not turn complete
if you just don't don't allow recursion
vo a lot recursion and you still want to
keep it not turing-complete then it
becomes harder and there are a lot of
more sophisticated languages which you
can deal with that I couldn't I just put
in my configuration file like while true
no op or something in it would well doll
doesn't have while loops it's a
functional programming language so what
it does have is terminating primitive
operations so example would be fold
alright so give it a list there's a
function called fold which will
basically sort of reduce the list into a
final value and we can prove for reasons
I won't go into that that function will
always terminate and then there are the
other theoretical results which show
that you can implement basically
anything you want to do with lists in
terms of fold more or less you might
want to do it in a more efficient way
but in theory you could do everything in
terms of fold
so if you can prove that all these
operations can be done in terms of fold
that you can prove that they can
terminate and then just that's how you
prove that your language just doesn't
terminate for anything built on top of
those primitive operations can I just
have two files import each other can I
make a loop that way no doll has a
cyclic I mean there are ways you can
cause a we call import cycles but that's
not one of them so doll will detect
trivial import cycles where it keeps
track of what important is visited and
make sure that they don't get visited
again
the but anyway you could break it is
just like have a web server hosting a
doll configuration file like example.com
slash one which imports example.com
slash 2/3 and you can just keep
dynamically generating these on the plot
on the fly to to trigger an infinite
import loop but again like that that
doesn't worry me so much for the same
reason that you know having a program
that takes too long to evaluate you know
doesn't worry me that much either right
it's just like I view it as primarily
improving the user experience by trying
by doing as much as possible to prevent
loops there's still some ways that you
can make things run a long time but as
long as we make a decent effort it still
improves the user experience
are there other languages and in common
usage or
or configuration formats the that have
this property of of being not
turing-complete yes actually the most
popular one which I think most people
know of is SQL that's a non Turing
complete language that's very very
widely used and for a reason again like
SQL because it's not your complete it's
easy for databases to analyze and do
like you know curry optimization and
things like that
a more modern example would be something
like skylark which is the languages I
think it's named skylark which is
language Bassel uses fur it's a
configuration language for builds those
are the two examples off the top of my
head I think sequel is interesting it
kind of shows some of the properties
you're talking about here because you
can define things in sequel like it
still has the feel of a programming
language but it's definitely more
restrictive in terms of what you can do
and focuses more on a declarative I mean
it's very different than your language
but it has some similarities I think
yeah so one thing I was wondering it
sounds like if I were to build like a
yeah mol parser you know where I could
read that format in because I have a new
programming language and it needs to
understand yeah mo that I think I could
do that to understand this configuration
format it sounds like in my language of
choice I would have to build like an
entire interpreter that understands
system FN and so on yes so yeah I mean
that's exactly one of the biggest
challenges for dolls that were
essentially trying to create an
embeddable language that runs in all
these mainstream languages right and if
they succeed they will actually be I
think one of the first ever case of that
being done because most other
configuration language is the way they
work is may be able provide some C
library like Lua than your languages
write some sort of a wrapper around the
C API like um you know some native
interface but here we're actually doing
implementations inside the host
languages like actual reimplementation
and it's significantly more challenging
but if it works then you can do powerful
things like I mentioned before like
import functions directly into the
language which is very neat you can also
provide much better support for
distribution right cuz like obviously
you can't use a C library if you want
interface with JavaScript right so it's
much more portable to do things this way
but it's much harder and so we spend a
lot of time on making
as easy as possible to port into new
languages so what languages have
implementations so currently there are
three complete implementations one in
Ruby one enclosure and one in Haskell
there are several other ones in progress
some close to completion but I'll wait
until they're done before announcing
them out of respect to their maintainer
x' and earlier you mentioned kubernetes
I guess I think what domains do you see
it all being used in ops is far and away
the most commonly used domain for dull
and the reason why is that that's where
you tend to see the largest and messiest
configurations the tools that come to
mind would be things like kubernetes
cloud formation templates ansible docker
compose terraform those are what a lot
of people tend to associate with this
and they all have very large messy gamal
or sometimes JSON configurations and
they kind of grown to the point where
they're starting to implement these you
know dsls which are like a little mini
programming languages inside them
especially CloudFormation ansible or
they also terraform come to mind there
and be so because they sort of like
hacked together this this
domain-specific language inside of JSON
or um well you get kind of the worst of
both worlds which is that it's really
difficult to understand because you
don't there's no editor tooling that
will tell you that you're you know -
that your confirmation template is like
it's a gauntlet program
right you can tell that it's it's well
form JSON right but that's not what you
who you're looking for right what you
really want is like a type checker or
more sophisticated syntax structure that
understands this domain-specific
language that they've built right you
don't you don't get that and you also
don't get the ability to like really you
can't really evaluate it easily right
you can you can run the tool right you
can run kubernetes and see like did I
die yeah me usually the way you verify
that your creations safe is you do like
a test deploy like to a development
cluster like this kubernetes or
something like right you don't have like
a nice pure way to do ahead of time
validation of your code and that's one
of the biggest issues that ops people
run into is that for them it's really
difficult to do safe test deploys
especially in CI
you don't want to like deploy it you
don't wanna like for every single
revision that you check into master the
first check that you can safely deploy
it you know a test development cost
that's totally unreleased realistic and
doesn't scale right the ideal would be
like you guys you just do type checking
right and if it type checks that's fast
you merge you're done and you know it's
going to deploy successfully so is that
the market that you're going after what
this tool would be optimum yes
absolutely so one thing I like to do and
this is actually inspired by a great
book which I recommend to all listeners
called crossing the chasm it's a book
that was originally written for startups
for how startups could achieve
mainstream traction success but it's
also an excellent playbook for tech
evangelist and we're getting open source
tools frameworks or technologies
mainstream traction as well and one of
the things the book talks about is that
you need to be very careful to choose a
very narrow market when you start out
piece you're not going to get any
mainstream traction
unless you're perceived to be
best-in-class for the use case that
you've chosen to address and you can't
be the best in class when you have very
limited development resources if you
choose to address a very broad use case
right if I said you know Dahl is gonna
be the configuration language that
replaces all configuration languages
right there's let that be too ambitious
you would we would sputter out pretty
early and we would never gain any
traction but it is very realistic for me
to say you know Dahl is gonna become the
best-in-class solution for obsolete
configurations we do have the developer
bandwidth and features you already be
able to deliver on that promise and if
we deliver on that and we promote that
perception then it's easier to then grow
into a slightly more broad or a use case
like maybe okay maybe later on we're a
tried displaced yamo in general as
opposed to just yell for ops so yes we
definitely do very conscientiously
target the ops use case and when we
designed the language and we when we
allocate our what we call our language
budget for like what complexity to agile
language we're very careful to add
language features which get us to that
goal of improving the ops experience
rather than trying to tackle a more
ambitious goal of being one
configuration language to roll them all
that's interesting what is an example of
a feature that you've added to make ops
better or
that you've taken this perspective on so
the biggest one would be semantic
integrity checks because that's the
thing that gives us people a lot of
assurance that what they're delivering
is never going to break or change the
semantics rhx verify that you can't
perturb something so it's safe and you
can also catch something so it's an easy
to subsequently redeploy sometimes it's
not about language features it can be
about integrations so for example we
have you know dolled kubernetes project
which provides bindings to kubernetes we
also provide tools that do
bi-directional conversion between Dahl
and JSON and llamó because for
brownfield deployments for large
enterprise companies these of migrations
really important it's also not about
even that kind of feature it's also
about like just things like how easy is
it to install is it just how easy is it
to obtain like is there a docker image
for it how big is the executable is it
statically linked how many platforms do
you support do you have a package for my
favorite operating system distribution
little details like that really all
contribute to in this case you know the
ops use case where they really care
about distribution it's a really big
deal for them very low dependencies ops
people hate things with lots of
dependencies because they're sort of
they're at the bottom of their company
stack everything depends on them so they
want to have as few of hesays as
possible why there's like often a flight
to things like bash or JSON and yamo
which are very dependency minimal and
that feature that you mentioned
generating Jason or yeah mole from your
from your doll configuration that sounds
like that would be very useful if I was
trying to like push adoption of this
right I wanted some flexibility I wanted
the ability to functions but my tool or
my team they still expect like a ya know
config yes so it makes it very easy to
integrate with tools that have a
hardwired man that things have to be
gamal in and I think one of the things
that has made doll really easy to get
into companies is because it doesn't
really require any permission from
leadership to try it out cuz like one of
I remember back when I was at Twitter
like I was a big hassle evangelist back
then never got it adopted and part of
the reason why it was so difficult to
get it adopted is just because the
Haskell tool chain is so hard to get
into the door
alright let's say we have these you know
CentOS machine
running a really old operating system
and they need to and then maybe they
want it to be and maybe they want jay-z
to be installed as a certain type of
package is appropriate for the operating
system and then even that you got to get
like get permission from the ops team to
get that package install and production
systems just so you could begin to use
let's say Haskell or our scripts let's
say where as like you know doll you can
just get it as a let's say three
megabyte Linux totally stacked linked
executable so like you it's just like
one curl away from being able to run it
on your system right so you don't really
need to ask anybody to try it out you
can use your pipelines without any real
permission from I mean you should get
permission from other people in general
but you can at least try it out and
demonstrate value without having to go
through any other teams to get it
installed and get it going and what what
is the thing that people have the most
problem with when they when they come to
it if I want to you know start using
this for my kubernetes config where
where will I get tripped up I think the
biggest issue people run into at the
moment is due to bottlenecks in the type
checker which we should be able to
resolve soon in a few months but I'll
still explain the problem which is that
in the Cooper days configuration one of
the big cells of Dolf or kubernetes is
that if it type checks in doll and then
you generate companies from that you
know you're not gonna get a bad
kubernetes configuration right I mean
your system could still break for
reasons they're specific to your company
right but at least you know it's gonna
be a valid kubernetes deployment a lot
of people really hate finding out that
the deployment broke at run time for
Google and so what they're trying to do
is they're trying to encode as much
information in dolls type system as
possible so the kubernetes the doll -
kubernetes project is I think one of the
larger dull open-source projects and I
think it has something around thirteen
thousand lines of code adult code and
because they're trying to they have a
very detailed and granular usage of the
types to make sure that if to make
invalid kubernetes configurations
unrepresentable
in doll so that people have as much
assurance in the generated Carre's
configuration but as a result that
really stresses the type checker both
because of the the granularity of the
types and also the size of the
configuration so we have people who are
currently working on
optimizing that and there's just worth
it needs to be done well I can see why
that would be a huge feature like
type-check you're you're cute configs
like that could be I could beat the tag
line right there obviously the language
does much more than that what a question
that was coming to my mind when I was
looking this over was like I understand
there's these problems with with having
repetition you know in your configs and
wanting this sort of flexibility it
doesn't seem to me like the obvious
solution was to write like a special
purpose you know non Turing complete
language where what are the roots of of
the idea behind this language yeah so
the language didn't originally start for
me saying like I want to make ops better
in fact when I created it it was more
just me trying to answer that academic
question are people okay with
programmable configuration languages if
they're not Turing complete and you can
see some of that in the in the language
design right so language has a very
Haskell like syntax because when I
originally made it I thought you'd only
be used to configure Haskell programs
right so it was optimized for that very
narrow market of Haskell programmers
that was originally trying to address
even narrow much narrower than ops I can
tell you so the syntax still is Haskell
like because of because of that origin
story but then a lot of people who
started using in Haskell you start to
for me like you know you're really onto
something and you could actually use
this for things like obsolete use cases
if you just took this all the way so I
just don't really like and so that
really encouraged me to invest more to
this project and try to make it
applicable to a much broader range of
users and try to make it a real thing
and now the main thing that sustains my
interest in this project even as the
scope continues to broaden is that I
really feel it's like a nice way to show
the value of total functional
programming especially with regards to
language security as you can see that
being like a really hot theme these days
with things like both cybersecurity
blockchain crypto currencies a lot of
people are not thinking a lot about
language security and what do we need to
do to make programming languages that
are easy to analyze e to understand easy
to secure and I feel like a lot of
language security principles haven't
really
made it to the mainstream because it
hasn't been like a killer app that has
taken it all the way and showing a
viable practical use case for it
I think Dahl can be one of those killer
apps showing the value of total
functional programming in language
security
you mentioned total functional
programming what I don't think we've
touched on that term yet oh yes
total functional programming is a
programming where I don't know what the
pedantic definition is but I think of it
as like programs that aren't going to
crash or hang or throw exceptions
meaning that evaluations if the program
type checks an evaluation will always
succeed because the see is kind of like
a UH it's almost kind of a broad word
but like for example like Dahl has
optional values kinda like knowable
values in programming languages right
and so like you know accommodation could
succeed and return with duck calls null
or none right some people might say like
that's still a failure right so if you
feel at runtime but it's still nice that
you it won't hang it won't crash or
throw exceptions or seg fall or what
have you if the in particularly if
things type check you just know it's
gonna work
right it's just one less thing to wake
you up in the middle of night or late on
weekends when you just want like I
really like software that is low
maintenance right that's kind of reason
one reason I got into Haskell in the
first place is I really loved that so I
really loved knowing that if adult
configuration type checks that I'm done
like my my obligations of programmer
ends there and I can move on to the next
thing
without you know that lingering in the
back of my mind that I might be
interrupted later on to revisit
something that I've sort of washed my
hands of so I just really like things
being done and total functional
programming really gives you that
feeling of satisfaction and completion
but you don't need to revisit old work
anymore it is interesting that you found
that Ops was the area where like heavy
use of a type system could really be a
game changer that's very interesting
insight well I shouldn't take the credit
for that cuz the only the only part
where my input was was figuring out that
would be good for configuration
languages because uh one of the things I
ran into early on when trying to design
what were the set of primitives for Dahl
is that it's very hard to figure out
like what what is this efficiently large
that are primitive
that our total but still useful enough
right so shiny think okay what's the
domain I'm trying to target here like
you like high performance computing or
or I don't know what have you now I was
like well what have I just said
configuration language is right because
the expectation there is so low that you
don't need to really have a very large
set of primitives to deliver on the
promise and then it also makes it much
easier to implement the language again
because if you want to have a portable
language in multiple with multiple
bindings we really need to keep the set
of primitives as low as possible so
configuration I chose just for ease more
than anything else
it was the users who then for me that
like this was really taking off in the
ops use case and that's when I begin to
realize that there was a fit between
types and reducing repetition and
maintainability and then this use case
of like these large and sprawling yellow
configurations and then I just really
lit lent into that oh that's great sorry
so Gabe I think that this has been a lot
of fun I've learned a lot and I think
the listeners will as well so thank you
for coming on the show thank you for
building Dahl where can listeners find
out more about you and about all the
best entry point to the language is the
official website which is Dahl - Lang
org if you don't know how to spell it
it's D H al l la ng org I have a blog
called Haskell for allcom although I
know I blog a little bit about dull more
often so I don't know if I should also
call it like Haskell and dull for allcom
but that's my personal blog that I
sometimes use this is adam gordon bell
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening as a software engineer
chances are you've crossed paths with
MongoDB at some point whether you're
building an app for millions of users
are just figuring out a side hustle as
the most popular non relational database
MongoDB is intuitive and incredibly easy
for development teams to use now with
MongoDB Atlas you can take advantage of
MongoDB flexible document data model as
a fully automated cloud service MongoDB
Atlas handles all the costly database
operations and admin tasks you'd rather
not spend time on like security high
availability data recovery monitoring
and elastic scaling
try MongoDB Atlas for free today visit
MongoDB dot-com / cloud to learn more
[Music]
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Archer police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening